JULIO ALBERTO VILLALTA

Summary

Dedicated professional with proven performance in management, leadership, and communication. Detail-oriented in problem-solving and planning. Ready to make an immediate contribution to your organization.

Skills

Leadership, Problem-solving, Critical-thinking, Project Management, Product Design, research expertise, Data Analytics, Presentation competency, Figma, UX/UI, Web Development, SEO, Database, APIs, REST.

Experience

Almacenes Siman / Head of Usability and Performance UX/UI

November 2020 - December 2023, El Salvador

- Spearheaded a UX/UI team of designers and developers to optimize website performance and enhance overall user experience, resulting in a 20% increase in user engagement.
- Conducted user research and usability testing to identify pain points and opportunities for improvement, leading to a 10% decrease in bounce rates.
- Implemented best practices for responsive design and mobile optimization, resulting in a 25% increase in mobile conversions.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams to prioritize and implement new features and enhancements, resulting in a 12% increase in click-through rate (CTR)
- Implemented automation tools to streamline operative processes by up to 50%.
- Established and monitored key metrics and KPIs to drive business decisions, provide analytical support, and improve the omnichannel commercial team

Garage Ventures USA, LLC / Founder and Head of Technology

May 2015-April 2020, Remote

- Contributed to a 20% annual increase in revenue for small tourism companies online.
- Our SaaS Tripper Booking System, managing bookings, inventory, and rates, helped optimize operations management for our customers by up to 60%.
- Developed a Content Management System (CMS) E-Commerce website for tourism companies, resulting in a 25% increase in our SaaS subscriptions and reduced churn rate.
- Implemented our own payment gateway using Stripe, PayPal, Pagadito, and other payment processors to increase the conversion rate by 30%.
- Successfully launched our online tourism marketplaces, bytto.com and Triviajo.com, resulting in a 30% increase in tour commissions and sales.
- Implemented Cloud with Google, Amazon, and Heroku, reducing costs by 30%.
- Adopted Agile methodologies including SCRUM, DevOps, and CI/CD with GitHub, GitLab, and Bitbucket, leading to a 40% increase in productivity.

Avianca / Innovation Specialist

September 2014-November 2014, El Salvador

- Leading innovation and the acquisition of new technologies to enhance business operations by 10% faster.
- Conducted training sessions on new trends and technologies, fostering a culture of continuous learning by 50%.
- Authored and achieved 80% of documentation of comprehensive reports on technological innovation, insights, and recommendations.

Avianca / Project Leader

November 2010-August 2014, El Salvador

- Managed Rapid Reprice project, an e-commerce strategic initiative that enabled online fee collection and ticket reissue, generating revenues of US\$2M.
- Managed the Frontend and Backend development of web platforms, ensuring the delivery of high-quality development with 100% compliance.
- Managed Fee Manager project, used in airports, offices, and call centers for extra baggage fees and ancillary, enhancing customer service and operational efficiency by up to 70%.
- Managed project lifecycles from planning and design to implementation and testing, ensuring projects meet deadlines by 95%, budgets, and quality standards.
- Managed projects with key industry suppliers including Travelport, Amadeus, and Imectech, resulting in an increase of revenue by up to 15%.

TACA Airlines / Project Coordinator

August 2008-November 2010, El Salvador

- Managed project, support and user experience (UX/UI) for the e-commerce website using MVC patterns with ASP.NET, resulting in a 10% increase in organic traffic.
- Managed IT projects and developed web applications, backend web services using Oracle, and MySQL databases, ASP.NET, SOA web services, resulting in a 20% reduction in costs.
- Achieved performance of 99% score for TACA's rebranded web, launching a new corporate website and a dedicated site for TACA Regional.

Education

The George Washington University / Specialization in E-commerce

September 2021-April 2022, USA (online)

FE Business School and University of Cadiz / MBA

November 2014-September 2015, Spain (Hybrid)

ESI School of Management/ Bachelor of Business Administration

February 2008-May 2013

Certifications Scrum Inc. / Registered Scrum Product Owner and Scrum Master

ID: RPO-3612638 / ID RSM-7223466

Google / Advanced Google Analytics & Google Tag Manager

ID: /analytics/academy/certificate/gTERvWbIR1G5rkibIZVI1w

Languages

Spanish - Native | English - Fluent C1

Portuguese — Intermediate B2 | French — Beginner A2

Personality

Team player, punctual, honest, diligent and organized, creative, problem solver, flexible, accountable, ethical.

Awards

March 2023 – SIMAN Excellence Award, recognition for excellent performance during 2022. March 2022 – SIMAN Excellence Award, recognition for excellent performance during 2021. March 2017 – Best Virtual Store in Tourism by Interlat and Hootsuite, Bogotá, Colombia. November 2016 — El Salvador Emprende award by governments of Taiwan and El Salvador.

